Let me talk about some other phenomena that have happened over the last few years.
지난 몇 년간 일어난 다른 현상들을 얘기해 보죠
One of them has been the rise and fall, perhaps of a new type of job called the Prompt engineer, someone
그중 하나가 흥망성쇠로 새로운 종류의 프롬프트 엔지니어로 llms에서 최고의
who specializes in knowing how to craft the right kind of prompts to get the best outcomes from llms.
결과를 얻기 위해 올바른 프롬프트 엔지니어를 만드는 데 전문인 사람이죠
At one point, this role commanded a $500,000 salary and was hot in demand.
한때 이 역할은 500,000달러의 연봉을 보장받았고 인기가 많았죠
It does seem to have fallen downwards a bit now.
비트가 좀 떨어진 것 같아요
The demand is less, partly because knowing how to prompt well has become ubiquitous.
수요가 less인 건 잘 진행하는 법을 아는 게 일상적이 됐기 때문이죠
There's so much content now about the right ways to go about prompting, and also because there are
요즘은 프롬프트와 관련된 콘텐츠가 아주 많습니다 프롬프트를
now tools that will actually create a prompt for you.
생성하는 툴도 많이 나오니까요
Anthropic, in fact, has has one of those tools.
앤트로픽은 그런 도구를 갖고 있어요
So it is now something that has become relatively common.
지금은 비교적 흔한 일이 됐죠
Another another phenomenon was the custom gpts.
또 다른 현상으로는 커스텀 gpt가 있었죠
OpenAI has a GPT store that was incredibly popular for a while.
오픈아이는 한동안 엄청난 인기를 끌었던 GPT 스토어를 운영했어요
It's become a little bit saturated at this point.
비트가 좀 더 풍부해졌어요
I think people became fatigued of building custom GPT, gpts, but it's still there.
사람들이 커스텀 GPT를 만드는 데 지친 것 같아요 하지만 gpt는 여전히 존재하죠
The GPT store is still reasonably popular, and you can go there to experiment with different kinds
GPT 스토어는 여전히 인기가 높습니다 다양한 gpt를
of tuned gpts.
실험해 볼 수 있죠
Then of course, still very important was the emergence of co-pilots ways in which a human and an LLM
또 아주 중요한 건 인간과 LLM이 협력할 수 있는 부조종사가 등장했다는
could collaborate together.
점이었죠
Famously, Microsoft Copilot, I think, was perhaps the first one that really took the world by storm.
유명한 얘기지만 마이크로소프트 부기장은 세상을 강타한 최초의 부기장이었을 거예요
GitHub copilot of course, and there are many more co-pilots that are being embedded into a lot of applications.
깃허브 부조종사도 물론이고요 많은 앱에 포함되고 있는 부조종사도 많아요
And in a way, we sort of saw that with canvas a moment ago.
조금 전에 캔버스로 그걸 봤어요
And then the new hot trend right now is all about agent ization, about using Agentic AI, which is
최근 트렌드는 에이전트 아이즈입니다 에이전트식 인공지능을 사용하는 거죠 여러 llms가
where multiple llms collaborate to solve a problem.
협력해 문제를 해결하는 거예요
A more complex problem is broken down into smaller steps or smaller tasks, and then particularly tuned
더 복잡한 문제는 더 작은 단계나 작은 작업으로 나뉘는데 특히 튜닝된 llm이
llms are used to tackle each of those steps, perhaps also with an LM responsible for planning and deciding
각 단계에 사용됩니다 LM은 계획과 어떤 LM이 뭘 하는지 결정하는 걸 책임지고요
Also, with a concept of memory, that there's some kind of persistent information that lasts, that
메모리 개념을 보면 지속적인 정보가 있고 LMS와
can be exchanged between the LMS and a sense of autonomy, that the LMS don't just exist for the purposes
자율성 사이에서 교환될 수 있습니다 LMS는 인간과의 채팅 인터페이스를
of a chat interface with a human, but they have a sort of time horizon that that spans multiple chats,
위해 존재하는 게 아니라 여러 채팅에 걸쳐 지속되는 시간 지평선이 있죠
So that sense of autonomy and memory and being able to plan tasks and divide tasks down, those are
자율성과 메모리 그리고 작업을 계획하고 나눌 수 있는 능력 이 모든 것이 에이전트적
all some of the core tenants of Agentic AI.
인공지능의 핵심 테넌트죠
And we'll be coming back to this a few times during the course, but in particular at the end of the
과정 중에 몇 번 더 다루겠지만 특히 8주 과정의 끝에서
course in week eight, we will build a full Agentic AI solution, as I might have said, a time or two,
에이전트식 인공지능 솔루션을 구축할 겁니다 한두 시간쯤 걸릴 거예요
but it's really great and it will have eight, seven, seven.
정말 훌륭하죠 8, 7, 7이 될 거예요
I don't get overexcited.
I'm go 과하게 흥분하지 않아요
There are seven agents that will collaborate as part of what we will build at the end.
마지막에 우리가 만들 것의 일부로 7명의 요원이 협력할 거예요